A Guide to the Project Records of the Virginia Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission, 1975-1985.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission, Virginia, Project Records
1975-1985.
The Library of Virginia
34596
Virginia. Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission.
8 cubic feet
Biographical/Historical Information
The Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission (JLARC) is responsible for legislative oversight and government accountability. The Commission studies and makes recommendations regarding program and agency savings, helps to improve agency efficiency and effectiveness, works to maintain an informed citizenry and legislature, and oversees agency compliance with legislative intent. The work of the Commission ensures that funds appropriated by the Virginia General Assembly are used effectively and efficiently by State and local agencies.
The Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission was created in 1973 and became operational in early 1974. The Commission is composed of nine members of the House of Delegates and five members of the Senate. At least five of the Delegates also serve on the House Appropriations Committee, and two of the Senators also serve on the Senate Finance Committee. Delegates are appointed by the Speaker of the House, and Senators by the Senate Rules Committee. The Chair is elected by a majority of Commission members and usually rotates every two years between the House and Senate. The Auditor of Public Accounts is a nonvoting, ex officio member. The Commission has a full-time staff led by a Director who is appointed by the Commission and confirmed by the General Assembly for a six-year term of office.
A fundamental change in evaluation authority occurred in 1977 with enactment of the Legislative Program Review and Evaluation Act. This act provided for a more systematic process of legislative oversight through a better defined topic selection process and direct involvement of General Assembly standing committees.
Scope and Content
These records document the research activities used to develop and write drafts and final reports on study issues. The studies focus around state agency functions and programs and evaluate their effectiveness and efficiency. They are retained to substantiate study findings, conclusions, recommendations and methodology, and to provide the data needed for comparative studies. Records include correspondence, working papers, survey instruments, reference materials, copies of data runs, extant agency documents and reports.
Arranged chronologically by report date. Records have been kept in their original order.
Acquisition Information
Accession 34596 was transferred by the Virginia Racing Commission, March 16, 1994.
Contents List
- Project Records, 1975-1985 (Accession 34596)., Extent: 8 cubic feet (8 boxes)
  - Virginia Community College System, 1975 March.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1975. (Box 1)
    - Printed Report, 1975 Mar. (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1975. (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1975. (Box 1)
    - Follow-up documents, 1975. (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous related reports, 1975. (Box 1)
  - Virginia Drug Abuse Control Programs, 1975 October.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1975. (Box 1)
    - Printed Report, 1975 Oct. (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1975. (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1975. (Box 1)
  - Working Capital Funds, 1976 Feb.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1975-1976. (Box 1)
    - Printed Report, 1976 Feb. (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1975-1976. (Box 1)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1975-1976. (Box 1)
  - Virginia Institute of Marine Science, 1976 July.
    - Printed Report, 1976 July. (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1976. (Box 1)
    - Status of action reports, 1976. (Box 1)
  - Water Resource Management, 1976 Sept.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1976. (Box 1)
    - Printed Report, 1976 Sept. (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1976. (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1976. (Box 1)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1976. (Box 1)
    - Status of action reports, 1976. (Box 1)
  - Vocational Rehabilitation, 1976 Nov.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1976. (Box 2)
    - Printed Report, 1976 Nov. (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1976. (Box 2)
    - Press releases, 1976. (Box 2)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1976. (Box 2)
    - Status of action reports, 1976. (Box 2)
  - Management of State-Owned Land, 1977 Apr.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1977. (Box 2)
    - Printed Report, 1977 Apr. (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1977. (Box 2)
    - Status of action reports, 1977. (Box 2)
  - Sunset-Zero-Base Budgeting Evaluation, 1977 May.
    - Records, 1977. (Box 2)
  - Zero-Base Budgeting, 1977 Aug.
    - Records, 1977. (Box 2)
  - Sunset Phenomenon, 1977 Dec.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1977. (Box 2)
    - Printed Report, 1977 Dec. (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1977. (Box 2)
    - Press releases, 1977. (Box 2)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1977. (Box 2)
    - Status of action reports, 1977. (Box 2)
  - Use of State-Owned Aircraft, 1977 Oct.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1977. (Box 2)
    - Printed Report, 1977 Oct. (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1977. (Box 2)
    - Status of action reports, 1977. (Box 2)
  - Long-Term Care in Virginia, 1978 Mar.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Printed Report, 1978 Mar. (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Press releases, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Status of action reports, 1978. (Box 3)
  - Medical Assistance Programs: An Overview, 1978 June.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Printed Report, 1978 June. (Box 3)
    - Press releases, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Status of action reports, 1978. (Box 3)
  - Virginia Supplemental Retirement System, 1978 Oct.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Printed Report, 1978 Oct. (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Press releases, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Status of action reports, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Follow-up reviews, 1978. (Box 3)
  - Capital Outlay Process, 1978 Oct.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Printed Report, 1978 Oct. (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Press releases, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Status of action reports, 1978. (Box 3)
  - Camp Pendleton, 1978 Nov.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Printed Report, 1978 Nov. (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Press releases, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1978. (Box 3)
    - Status of action reports, 1978. (Box 3)
  - Inpatient Care in Virginia, 1979 Jan.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1978-1979. (Box 4)
    - Printed Report, 1979 Jan. (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1978-1979. (Box 4)
    - Press releases, 1978-1979. (Box 4)
    - Status of action reports, 1978-1979. (Box 4)
  - Outpatient Care in Virginia, 1979 Mar.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Printed Report, 1979 Mar. (Box 4)
    - Press releases, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Status of action reports, 1979. (Box 4)
  - Management and Use of State-Owned Motor Vehicles, 1979 July.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Printed Report, 1979 July. (Box 4)
    - Newpaper clippings, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Status of action reports, 1979. (Box 4)
  - Certificate of Need in Virginia, 1979 Aug.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Printed Reports, 1979 Aug. (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Press releases, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Status of action reports, 1979. (Box 4)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University Extension Division, 1979 Sept.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Printed Report, 1979 Sept. (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Press releases, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Status of action reports (Volume I of II), 1979. (Box 4)
    - Status of action reports (Volume II of II), 1979. (Box 4)
  - Deinstitutionalization of the Mentally Ill and Mentally Retarded, 1979 Sept.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Printed Report, 1979 Sept. (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Press releases, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous items, 1979. (Box 4)
  - Report to the General Assembly, 1979 Sept.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1979. (Box 4)
    - Printed Report, 1979 Sept. (Box 4)
  - Homes for Adults, 1979 Dec.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1979. (Box 5)
    - Printed Report, 1979 Dec. (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1979. (Box 5)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1979. (Box 5)
    - Status of action reports, 1979. (Box 5)
  - Federal Funds Reports, 1979 Dec-1981 Jan.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1979-1981. (Box 5)
    - Printed Reports, 1979-1981. (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1979-1981. (Box 5)
    - Status of action reports, 1979-1981. (Box 5)
  - Operational Overview - Management Consultants by State Agencies, 1980 May.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1980. (Box 5)
    - Printed Report, 1980 May. (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1980. (Box 5)
    - Press releases, 1980. (Box 5)
    - Status of action reports, 1980. (Box 5)
  - The General Relief Program in Virginia, 1980 Sept.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1980. (Box 5)
    - Printed Report, 1980 Sept. (Box 5)
    - Press releases, 1980. (Box 5)
    - Status of action reports, 1980. (Box 5)
  - Methodology for a Vehicle Cost Responsibility Study, 1981 Jan (Senate Document 12).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1980-1981. (Box 5)
    - Printed Report, 1981 Jan. (Box 5)
    - Press releases, 1980-1981. (Box 5)
  - Organization and Administration of the Department of Highways and Transportation, 1981 Jan and Nov (Senate Documents 7 and 14).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1980-1981. (Box 5)
    - Printed Reports, 1981 Jan and Nov. (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Press releases, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Status of action reports, 1981. (Box 5)
  - Title XX in Virginia, 1981-Jan.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1980-1981. (Box 5)
    - Printed Report, 1981 Jan. (Box 5)
  - Organization and Administration of Social Services, 1981 Apr.
    - Printed Report, 1981 Apr. (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1981. (Box 5)
  - Report to the General Assembly, 1981 Oct.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Printed Report, 1981 Oct. (Box 5)
    - Status of action requests, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Follow-up documents, 1981. (Box 5)
  - Summar Report: Highway and Transportation Programs, 1981 Nov (Senate Document 6).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Printed Report, 1981 Nov. (Box 5)
  - Highway Construction, Maintenance, and Transit Needs in Virginia, 1981 Nov (Senate Document 8).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Printed Report, 1981 Nov. (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1981. (Box 5)
  - Vehicle Cost Responsibility, 1981 Nov (Senate Document 13).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Printed Report, 1981 Nov. (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Press releases, 1981. (Box 5)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1981. (Box 5)
  - Highway Financing in Virginia, 1981 Nov (Senate Document 14).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1981. (Box 6)
    - Printed Report, 1981 Nov. (Box 6)
  - Publications and Public Relations of State Agencies, 1982 Jan (Senate Document 23).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1981-1982. (Box 6)
    - Printed Report, 1982 Jan. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1981-1982. (Box 6)
    - Status of action reports, 1981-1982. (Box 6)
  - Occupational and Professional Regulatory Boards in Virginia, 1982 Jan (Senate Document 29).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1981-1982. (Box 6)
    - Printed Report, 1982 Jan. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1981-1982. (Box 6)
  - The CETA Program Administered by Virginia's Balance-of-State Prime Sponsor, 1982 May (House Document 3).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982. (Box 6)
    - Printed Report, 1982 May. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982. (Box 6)
  - Working Capital Funds in Virginia, 1982 June (House Document 4).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982. (Box 6)
    - Printed Report, 1982 June. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982. (Box 6)
  - The Occupational and Professional Regulatory System in Virginia, 1982 Dec (Senate Document 3).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982. (Box 6)
    - Printed Report, 1982 Dec. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982. (Box 6)
    - Status of action reports, 1982. (Box 6)
  - Interim Report: Equity of Current Provisions for Allocating Construction Funds in Virginia, 1982 Dec (House Document 17).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982. (Box 6)
    - Printed Report, 1982 Dec. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982. (Box 6)
  - Consolidation of Office Space in Roanoke, 1983 Jan (Senate Document 15).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982-1983. (Box 6)
    - Printed Report, 1983 Jan. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982-1983. (Box 6)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1982-1983. (Box 6)
  - Staffing and Manpower Planning the Department of Highways, 1983 Jan (House Document 18).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982-1983. (Box 6)
    - Printed Report, 1983 Jan. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982-1983. (Box 6)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1982-1983. (Box 6)
  - Local Mandates and Financial Resources: Interim Report, 1983 Jan (House Document 40) and Final Report, 1983 Dec (House Document 15).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982-1983. (Box 6)
    - Printed Reports, 1983 Jan and Dec. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982-1983. (Box 6)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1982-1983. (Box 6)
  - Organization of the Executive Branch: Interim Report, 1983 Jan (House Document 36) and An Assessment of Structural Targets in the Executive Branch: Final Report, 1984 Jan (House Document 20).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982-1984. (Box 6)
    - Printed Reports, 1983 Jan and 1984 Jan. (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982-1984. (Box 6)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1982-1984. (Box 6)
  - The Economic Potential and Management of Virginia's Seafood Industry, 1983 Jan (House Document 2).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982-1983. (Box 7)
    - Printed Report, 1983 Jan. (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1982-1983. (Box 7)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1982-1983. (Box 7)
    - Status of action reports, 1982-1983. (Box 7)
  - Follow-up Report on the Virginia Department of Highways, 1983 Jan (House Document 34).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1982-1983. (Box 7)
    - Printed Report, 1983 Jan. (Box 7)
    - Status of action reports, 1982-1983. (Box 7)
  - Report to the General Assembly, 1983 Oct.
    - Printed Report, 1983 Oct. (Box 7)
    - Status of action reports, 1983. (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous: Teams' remarks about status of actions responses, 1983. (Box 7)
  - The Virginia Division for Children, 1983 Dec (House Document 14).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1983. (Box 7)
    - Printed Report, 1983 Dec. (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1983. (Box 7)
  - The Virginia Division of Volunteerism, 1983 Dec (Senate Document 6).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1983. (Box 7)
    - Printed Report, 1983 Dec. (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1983. (Box 7)
  - An Assessment of the Secretarial System in the Commonwealth, 1984 Jan (House Document 21).
    - Printed Report, 1984 Jan. (Box 7)
  - An Assessment of the Roles of Boards and Commissions in the Executive Branch of Virginia, 1984 Jan (House Document 22).
    - Printed Report, 1984 Jan. (Box 7)
  - Summary Report: Organization of the Executive Branch of Virginia, 1984 Jan (House Document 44).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1983-1984. (Box 7)
    - Printed Report, 1984 Jan. (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1983-1984. (Box 7)
  - Follow-up Report on the Virginia Department of Highways and Transportation, 1984 Jan (House Document 23).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1983-1984. (Box 7)
    - Printed Report, 1984 Jan. (Box 7)
    - Status of action reports, 1983-1984. (Box 7)
  - Interim Report: Central and Regional Office Staffing in the Department of Corrections, 1984 May (House Document 41).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1984. (Box 7)
    - Printed Report, 1984 May. (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1984. (Box 7)
  - Interim Report: Central and Regional Office Staffing in the Department of Corrections, 1984 May (House Document 41).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1984. (Box 7)
    - Printed Report, 1984 May. (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1984. (Box 7)
  - Equity of the Current Provisions for Allocating Highway and Transportation Funds in Virginia, 1984 June (House Document 11) and Recommendations Related Thereto, 1984 Dec.
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1984. (Box 7)
    - Printed Reports, 1984 June and Dec. (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1984. (Box 7)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1984. (Box 7)
  - Special Education in Virginia's Training Centers for the Mentally Retarded, 1984 Nov (Senate Document 2) and Special Education in Virginia's Mental Health Facilities, 1984 Nov (Senate Document 4).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1984. (Box 8)
    - Printed Reports, 1984 Nov. (Box 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1984. (Box 8)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1984. (Box 8)
    - Status of action reports, 1984. (Box 8)
  - ADP Contracting at the State Corporation Commission, 1984 Nov (House Document 4).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1984. (Box 8)
    - Printed Report, 1984 Nov. (Box 8)
  - The Virginia State Library's Contract with The Computer Company, 1984 Nov (House Document 5).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1984. (Box 8)
    - Printed Report, 1984 Nov. (Box 8)
  - The Virginia Tech Library System, 1984 Nov (House Document 6).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1984. (Box 8)
    - Printed Report, 1984 Nov. (Box 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1984. (Box 8)
  - Patent and Copyright Issues in Virginia State Government, 1985 Mar (House Document 31).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Printed Report, 1985 Mar. (Box 8)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous: Follow-up documents, 1985. (Box 8)
  - Virginia's Correctional System: Population Forecasting and Capacity, 1985 Apr (House Document 36).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Printed Report, 1985 Apr. (Box 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1985. (Box 8)
  - The Community Diversion Incentive Program of the Virginia Department of Corrections, 1985 Apr (House Document 35).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Printed Report, 1985 Apr. (Box 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous: Follow-up documents, 1985. (Box 8)
  - Security Staffing and Procedures in Virginia's Prisons, 1985 July (House Document 3).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Printed Report, 1985 July. (Box 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1985. (Box 8)
  - Towns in Virginia, 1985 July (House Document 2) and Local Fiscal Stress and State Aid, 1985 Aug (House Document 4).
    - Commission Meeting Minutes, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Printed Reports, 1985 July and Aug. (Box 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1985. (Box 8)
  - Report to the General Assembly, 1985 Sept.
    - Printed Report, 1985 Sept. (Box 8)
    - Status of action requests, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Agency responses (Volume I of II), 1985. (Box 8)
    - Agency responses (Volume II of II), 1985. (Box 8)
    - Follow-up documents, 1985. (Box 8)
  - The Virginia Housing Development Authority Interim Progress Report, 1985 Feb and Final Report, 1985 Oct.
    - Commission Metting Minutes, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Printed Reports, 1985 Feb and Oct. (Box 8)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Record of related legislative actions, 1985. (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous: Follow-up documents, 1985. (Box 8)